within a year of the Gezi protests with comfortable margins. To be sure, governments have different resources to bring to the table. It's not the same game, but the differences are instructive. And like all such stories, this is not a story just of technology. It's what technology allows us to do converging with what we want to do. Today's social movements want to operate informally. They do not want institutional leadership. They want to stay out of politics because they fear corruption and cooptation. They have a point. Modern representative democracies are being strangled in many countries by powerful interests. But operating this way makes it hard for them to sustain over the long term and exert leverage over the system, which leads to frustrated protesters dropping out, and even more corrupt politics. And politics and democracy without an effective challenge hobbles, because the causes that have inspired the modern recent movements are crucial. Climate change is barreling towards us. Inequality is stifling human growth and potential and economies. Authoritarianism is choking many countries. We need movements to be more effective. Now, some people have argued that the problem is today's movements are not formed of people who take as many risks as before, and that is not true. From Gezi to Tahrir to elsewhere, I've seen people put their lives and livelihoods on the line. It's also not true, as Malcolm Gladwell claimed, that today's protesters form weaker virtual ties. No, they come to these protests, just like before, with their friends, existing networks, and sometimes they do make new friends for life. I still see the friends that I made in those Zapatista-convened global protests more than a decade ago, and the bonds between strangers are not worthless. When I got tear-gassed in Gezi, people I didn't know helped me and one another instead of running away. In Tahrir, I saw people, protesters, working really hard to keep each other safe and protected. And digital awareness-raising is great, because changing minds is the bedrock of changing politics. But movements today have to move beyond participation at great scale very fast and figure out how to think together collectively, develop strong policy proposals, create consensus, figure out the political steps and relate them to leverage, because all these good intentions and bravery and sacrifice by itself are not going to be enough. And there are many efforts. In New Zealand, a group of young people are developing a platform called Loomio for participatory decision making at scale. In Turkey, 140Journos are holding hack-a-thons so that they support communities as well as citizen journalism. In Argentina, an open-source platform called DemocracyOS is bringing participation to parliaments and political parties. These are all great, and we need more, but the answer won't just be better online decision-making, because to update democracy, we are going to need to innovate at every level, from the organizational to the political to the social. Because to succeed over the long term, sometimes you do need tea without sugar along with your Twitter. Thank you. (Applause)
un año después de las protestas en Gezi, con una ventaja considerable. Los gobiernos tienen otro tipo de recursos que tienen a su disposición que no son lo mismo, pero de las diferencias se aprende. Y como todas las historias de este tipo, aquí no se trata solo de la tecnología. Es lo que nos permite la tecnología hacer y lo que queremos hacer. Los movimientos sociales actuales operan de manera informal. No quieren una dirección institucionalizada. No se involucran en la política, por temor a la corrupción y cooptación. Y tienen razón. Las democracias representativas modernas están asfixiadas en muchos países por intereses poderosos. Pero actuar de esta manera hace que sea difícil una movilización a largo plazo y ejercer presión sobre el sistema que lleva a los manifestantes frustrados a renunciar y a más corrupción en la política. Y la política y la democracia sin un desafío eficaz cojean, porque las causas que han inspirado los recientes movimientos modernos son cruciales. El cambio climático está aquí. La desigualdad asfixia el crecimiento humano, el potencial y las economías. El autoritarismo está en las últimas en muchos países. Necesitamos que los movimientos sean más eficaces. Ahora, algunas personas han argumentado que el problema es que los movimientos de hoy en día los forman personas que no asumen tantos riesgos como antes, y eso no es cierto. Desde Gezi a Tahrir a otros lugares, he visto a la gente poner sus vidas y sus medios de vida en juego. Tampoco es cierto, como afirma Malcolm Gladwell, que los manifestantes de hoy formar lazos virtuales más débiles. No, ellos vienen a estas protestas, al igual que antes, con sus amigos, las redes existentes, ya veces hacen nuevos amigos de por vida. Todavía veo a los amigos que me hice en las protestas globales convocadas ya hace más de una década, y los vínculos entre extraños tienen valor. Cuando me rociaron con gas lacrimógeno en Gezi, la gente que yo no conocía de nada me ayudó y también a los demás, en lugar de huir. En Tahrir, vi a personas, los manifestantes, trabajando muy duro para protegerse entre sí y estar seguros. Y la sensibilización digital es fantástica porque cambiar mentalidades es la piedra angular de la evolución de la política. Pero los movimientos de hoy tienen que ir más allá de la participación a gran escala y encontrar la manera pensar juntos colectivamente, desarrollar fuertes propuestas políticas, crear consenso, averiguar los pasos políticos y relacionarlos para aprovecharlos porque todas estas buenas intenciones y la valentía y el sacrificio por sí mismas no van a ser suficientes. Y se hacen muchos esfuerzos. En Nueva Zelanda, un grupo de jóvenes están desarrollando una plataforma llamada Loomio para decisiones participativas a escala. En Turquía, 140Journos son la celebración de los maratones informáticos para apoyar a las comunidades así como el periodismo ciudadano. En Argentina, una plataforma de código abierto llamada DemocracyOS está ayudando al parlamento y a los partidos políticos. Estos son todos ejemplos fantásticos, y necesitamos más, pero la respuesta no será solo una toma de decisiones online. porque para actualizar la democracia, vamos a necesitar innovar en todos los niveles, de lo organizativo a lo político y a lo social. Debido a que para tener éxito a largo plazo, a veces hace falta un té sin azúcar junto a su Twitter. Gracias. (Aplausos)